A Guide to the Papers of John McLaren McBryde, 1900-1907
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
- Talbott-VanCourt, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:178)
  - c: Letter in reference to changing the attitude at V.P.I. toward having more respect for agriculture.
  - d: Notable letterhead from the Bugle V.P.I., 1907.
  - e: Paper titled, "A Plain Talk on Education." Compliments faculty and the education received at V.P.I. stating that V.P.I. should be a model school in every detail for learning engineering, 1905.
  - f: Notable official letterhead from the Bugle, 1907.
  - g: Notable letterhead from the Vermont Farm Machine Co., 1906.
- Original Documents from folder 178: Talbott-VanCourt, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:179)
- Wade-Watkins, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:180)
  - a: Letter concerning a sales person on campus violating his contract to only sell books, 1906.
  - b: Letter referring to a woman having Hysterical Paralysis and a discussion of cases in Europe, 1907.
  - c: Letter to McBryde from F.S.Walker requesting a recommendation for a job as principal of the new State Agricultural College for the Sixth Georgia District, 1907.
  - d: Letter from G.F. Walters Bureau of Navigation, Navy Department requesting a circular that was sent out regarding the building of Dairy Barns, 1907.
  - e: Letter from the United States Power Depot, O.B. Witeman Lt. Col., 1907.
  - f: Series of letters and circulars concerning ordinances and the War Department.
  - g: Circulars from the War Department office of the Chief of Ordinance pertaining to the "Act to amend Section 1225 of revised statutes, so as to provide for detail of retires officers of the Army and Navy to assist in Military instruction schools."
  - h: Notable letterhead from the First National Bank, 1906.
  - i: Notable letterhead from the Northwest Farm and Home, North Yakima, Washington, 1907.
  - j: Letter to Dr. Barringer from J.B. Watkins in reference to a Horticulture meeting which had a resolution to request the Legislature to amend or repeal the Present Crop Pest Law, 1907.
- McBryde, President John. (Box-folder 5:181)
  - a: Miscellaneous letters directed to McBryde from parents of students.
  - b: Letter from Mrs Sykes about son's language classes. The 3rd quoted letter in the book The First 100 Years: A history of V.P.I. by Duncan Lyle Kinnear, 1972.
  - c: Letter from a mother, the 8th quoted letter in the previously mentioned publication, 1903.
  - d: Letter from a farmer, is the 16th letter quoted in the previously mentioned publication, 1892.
  - e: Letter from J.H. Squires in regards to his returning to finish his education after being discharged, 1904.
  - f: Letter from a former student, the 11th quoted letter in the previously mentioned publication, 1903.
- Hazing, 1899-1905. (Box-folder 5:182)
  Scope and Content
  The contents of this folder are in folder 223 in box 7 of the McBryde Collection.
- Womack-Wing and Son, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:183)
  - a: Letter addressed to Barringer from a distant relative, Margaret Miller Webb regarding her son, 1907.
  - b: Notable letterhead from Weber Steel-Concrete Chimney Co., 1907.
  - c: Letter from the Chairman Executive Committee in Athens Georgia asking questions of V.P.I.'s income, size and governmental relations being a Land- Grant college, 1906. Following is a response with all the answers.
  - d: Letter regarding financial difficulties being the hold-up in fixing the problems with lighting and heat at V.P.I., 1907.
  - e: Correspondence with Edgar C. Wiley about the improvement of light, heat and power plant at V.P.I., 1907.
  - f: Letter to Mr. A.D. Williams as he was being appointed assistant in Civil Engineering, 1906.
  - g: Letter concerning the sleeping arrangements made for the cadets for the Jamestown Exposition, 1907.
  - h: Letter to Mr. H.H.Wilson as he was being given a place as assistant in Civil Engineering, 1906, along with his letter of interest and several letters of recommendation.
  - i: Notable letterhead from Wing & Son, 1906.
- Winton-Zerkel, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 5:184)
  - a: Letter to a parent concerning the infirmary fees, 1907.
  - b: Letter concerning the resignation of Dr. Soule, 1907.
  - c: Letter to Mr. Wood stating that he had been re-appointed an instructor in biology and horticulture, 1906.
  - d: Letter to Mr. H. Worthington about his re-appointment to instructor in the modern language department, 1906.
  - e: Notable letterhead from E.A. Wright, 1907.
- McBryde, Annual Report, 1905. (Box-folder 5:185)
- Investigation, June 7, 1902. (Box-folder 5:186)
- From Folder 1: McBryde, John, President. (Box-folder 6:187)
  - a: Review of the University. History, makeup and letters commending the university for its turn out of good workers.
- From Folder 2: Untitled. (Box-folder 6:188)
  - a: Overview of the Department of Agriculture and Immigration.
  - b: Copy of the V.P.I. statistics of attendance, Etc.
  - c: Copy of four documents with the requirements for B.S. degrees in General Science, Agriculture, Mechanical Engineering and Electrical Engineering.
  - d: Manufacturers record, Jnauary 23, 1902.
  - e: Schedule of final examinations session, 1903-1904.
  - f: Article written about the University for an article in Scientific American Encyclopedia.
  - g: Memorandum of Working Agreement Between the State Board of Control of Virginia and the Bureau of Animal Industry for the Control of Southern Cattle and the Eradication of Ticks Which Transmit Southern Cattle Fever.
  - h: Article on the "Programme" for the farmers' institute.
  - i: Petition signed by the school trustees of the public school on Albemarle County, their statement on the boundary changes proposal.
  - j: Paper on the establishment and the history of the veterinary department.
  - k: A bill to apply a portion of public money to the betterment of college programs.
- From Folder 4: Correspondence (t. McBryde), 1902-1907. (Box-folder 6:189)
  - a: Synopsis of the experiment work outlined for a three year span at the experiment station.
- From Folder 6: Correspondence, 1902-1907. (Box-folder 6:190)
  - a: Statements with regard to the investigation of the dining hall and the heating of the barracks.
  - b: Letter from W.E. Barlow, head of the Metallurgy and Industrial Chemistry department, to the Board of Visitors asking for full professor status, ability to make additions to his equipment, and request for a laboratory assistant.
  - c: Annual report of the department of Metallurgy and Metallography, May 1907.
- From Folder 7: Junior Class Resignation, December 1904-January 1905. (Box-folder 6:191)
  - a: Original Petition signed by the Junior class resigning from the institution.
- From Folder 8: Faculty-Student matters. (Box-folder 6:192)
  - a: An answer to the petition of the Senior class asking for certain privileges.
- From Folder 11: Reports on School - addressed to BOV, 1902-1908. (Box-folder 6:193)
  - a: Individual reports from various departments of the Scientific Department and summation.
  - b: Three reports of the Treasurer: July 1898, July 1902 and July 1904.
  - c: Letter of statements of the financial transactions of the Institute from June 10, 1901 to June 10, 1902.
  - d: Specifications for the experimental barn for the Virginia Polytechnic Institute.
  - e: Two reports of the Treasurer: July 1901, and July 1903.
  - f: Report of the Associate Professor of Metallurgy, Metallography and Industrial Chemistry, for the academic year 1905-1906.
- From Folder 13: Reports. (Box-folder 6:194)
  - a: Miscellaneous correspondence.
- From Folder 14: Annual Reports. (Box-folder 6:195)
  - a: Hartford Steam Boiler Inspection and Insurance.
  - b: Report to the Board of Visitors of the work in Theoretic Kinematics, Valve and Mechanical Laboratory through Professor Randolph.
- From Folder 15: Fire Losses / Barringer letter, 1905-1907. (Box-folder 6:196)
  - a: Department of Physics, list of items and prices lost in the fire.
  - b: Department of Metallurgy, estimated loss from the fire.
- From Folder 16: Boiler 1905-06- Ag Hall (Plans for). (Box-folder 6:197)
  - a: Hartford Steam Boiler Insurance and Inspection July and December of 1906.
- From Folder 17: Chimney Company, Ag Hall, 1905-1906. (Box-folder 6:198)
  - a: Weber Steel-Concrete Chimney Company Specifications and Proposal.
  - b: Blue Print of chimney.
  - c: Weber Chimneys partial list of customers.
- From Folder 20: Plumbing Specs.- Ag Hall. (Box-folder 6:199)
  - a: Proposal for an automatic ice and refrigerating machinery. Ice Machine Supply Co.
  - b: Specifications for refrigerating and ice making plant. The Carbondale Machine Company.
  - c: Information sheet to the Ruemmeli-Dawley Mfg. Co.
- From Folder 22: Government Correspondence. (Box-folder 6:200)
  - a: Petition from Hatton Ferry and depot asking for special privilege of crossing the James River with ox teams to haul produce to the depot.
  - b: An Act approved by the State Assembly of Virginia to regulate the sale of "Spirituous of intoxicating or malt liquors to minors and students."
- From Folder 23: Miscellaneous- McBryde's Interest. (Box-folder 6:201)
  - a: Baltimore paper review of Scottish song and story of Miss Amy Murray.
  - b: Copy of fold out brochure on Miss Amy Murray, with photo on the front.
- From Folder 28: Ambrose-N.W. Ayer & Son Advertising, 1900-1904. (Box-folder 6:202)
  - a: One letter from parent of a student.
- From Folder 36: Coken- Coutuery, 1901-1904. (Box-folder 6:203)
  - a: Letter form the Republic of Argentina.
- From Folder 49: Gray-Gualthaney. (Box-folder 6:204)
  - a: Sample membership cards from the Globe-Wernicke Co.
  - b: Brochure on Globe-Wernicke Co.
- From Folder 59: Lachlan-Lilley, 1901-1904. (Box-folder 6:205)
  - a: Letter from Troy Laundry Machinery Co. Ltd. quoting prices for various machines.
- From Folder 60: Lilley-Lyon, 1901-1904. (Box-folder 6:206)
  - a: Miscellaneous correspondence.
- From Folder 66: Miller-Moore, 1901-1904. (Box-folder 6:207)
  - a: Report submitted to The Inspector General following an inspection of the government property at V.P.I.
- From Folder 70: Patton-Payne. (Box-folder 6:208)
- From Folder 80: Sheldon-Smidon. (Box-folder 6:209)
- From Folder 92: Ware-White. (Box-folder 6:210)
- From Folder 100: Applications for employment by students, 1900-1901. (Box-folder 6:211)
- From Folder 101: Problems, A-K, 1902-1903. (Box-folder 6:212)
  - a: A review written by Drinkard about the lawlessness and disorder that was breaking out 1902.
- From Folder 104: Bason-Butt, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 6:213)
  - a: Newspaper article titled: " Crush Rowdyism Say Educators."
- From Folder 105: Calvert-Cunnigham, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 6:214)
- From Folder 108: Hall-Huffard, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 6:215)
  - a: Pamphlet on Property for sale or lease, possibility of a College, Sanitarium, Asylum or School, located in Washington D.C.
- From Folder 134: Palmer-Tuok, Campbell, 1905-1906. (Box-folder 6:216)
- From Folder 140: Reports on delinquent or unsatisfactory students, 1907-1908. (Box-folder 6:217)
  - a: Petition from the class of 1909 to be permitted to wear the present senior uniform instead of changing to the new uniform as planned.
  - b: Requests to leave campus.
  - c: Reports on delinquent students.
  - d: Explanations for absences (official form.)
  - e: Copies of the official letter sent to parents when their son had too many demerits.
  - f: Professors reports.
  - g: Reports sent to the Commandant's office.
- From Folder 162: McBryde Miscellaneous. (Box-folder 6:218)
  - a: Report of appropriations and Expenditures since 1891.
- From Folder 144: Clothier-Cuthorell, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 6:219)
  - a: Letter referring to the trip to Charleston exhibition with the Corps, 1901-1902.
- From Folder 157: Kaatz-Kyle, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 6:220)
- From Folder 159: Lochicotte-Lueckel, McBryde-Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 6:221)
  - a: Hartford Steam Boiler Inspection and Insurance, August 1907.
- From Folder 160: Mabey-McCoy, McBryde-Barringer, 1906-1907. (Box-folder 6:222)
- From Folder 182: Hazing, 1899-1902. (Box-folder 6:223)
  - a: resolution of the Freshman Class December 6, 1899 stating that no single member of the class has been injured or inconvenienced in any way by hazing. Letter written as a result of the a newspaper article written about a boy from Portsmouth who sustained injuries at V.P.I. as a result of hazing and couldn't return.
  - b: Petition drawn up by the senior class and signed by the representatives from the class of 1900, 1901, 1902, 1903, to do everything in their power to uphold the trustees and faculty in their legislation on hazing.
  - c: Letter from the committee appointed by the class of 1903 submit the findings of their investigation of the Brandenburg Case.
  - d: Letter in response to a paragraph written in the Richmond Dispatch about hazing at V.P.I.
  - e: Copies of letters from a son to his father in reference to hazing.
  - f: A letter from the freshman class titled "A Move in the Right Direction."
  - g: Petition to the president referring to the "hair cutting incident" and hazing.
  - h: Each class evaluation and decision on the "hair cutting incident."
- Hazing, Dr. McBryde, 1904-1905. (Box-folder 6:224)
  - a: Letter from a parent about the condition of her son after returning from V.P.I.
  - b: Letter from a son to his parents with accounts of hazing and abuse.
  - c: Letter from The News Leader about a former students story of hazing and food problems at V.P.I.
  - d: Letter from Governor Montague about the hazing problem at V.P.I.
  - e: Resolutions to be adopted by the senior class.
  - f: Petitions from the sophomore and junior class to stop hazing.
- Newspaper articles on the Pace hazing incident, 1899. (Box-folder 6:225)
- Bids and Contracts, 1900-1907. (Box-folder 6:226)
- Bids and Contracts, 1900-1907. (Box-folder 6:227)
  - a: Contract with coal producers.
  - b: Orders and prices for J.P. Bell Company, Publisher, Stationers, Painters and Binders.
  - c: Notable letterhead for The Stone Printing & Mfg. Co., 1903.
  - d: Comparison of bids from various companies for catalogue for 1899-1900.
  - e: Notable letterhead from Hammonds Printing Works, 1900.
  - f: Notable letterhead for The Stone Printing & Manufacturing Co.
  - g: Notable letterhead for The Moose Bros Company, 1902.
  - h: Notable letterhead from J.A. Wilkins Printing Company.
  - i: Contract stating that V.P.I. authorizes the construction of a dwelling house on the campus, for the use of Professor John R. Fair.
  - j: A blank contract for V.P.I.
  - k: Synopses of illustrated lectures by Roberts Harper, F.R.G.S., a choice of seven lectures.
  - l: Notable letterhead from Bernstein Manufacturing Co.
  - m: Subscription contract for Men of Mark in Virginia. (Notable letterhead.)
  - n: Notable letterhead for U.S. Mail Bag Manufacturer, 1902.
  - o: Specifications submitted by Art Metal Construction Co. for steel shelving and files at V.P.I., submitted May 1904.
  - p: Contracts for the uniforms.
  - q: Pamphlet/ price list of cotton duck at John Boyle & Co.
  - r: Notable letterhead for Miller, Bain, Beyer & Co., 1901.
  - s: Jobbers price list of Belding Bros. & Co. Silk manufacturers, 1899.
- Original Documents from folder 102: Ligon-Wade McBryde Problems, 1902-1903. (Box-folder 6:228)
- Original Documents from folder 120: Eastman-Frost, McBryde, 1905. (Box-folder 6:229)
- Account vouchers, 1901. (Box 6)
- Publications (Box 6)
- Letter books from the McBryde administration, 1900-1906. (Box 7; 8)
- Oversize Materials from the McBryde Collection. (Box 9)
  - From Box 1 Folder 2: Untitled.
    - a: Statistics of Attendance for V.P.I.
    - b: Four Check off lists for a B.S. degree in Mechanical Engineering, Agriculture, Electrical Engineering and General Science.
    - c: Advertisement with sample work from Sanders Engraving Co., 1900.
  - From Box 1 Folder 20: Plumbing Specs., Ag. Hall.
    - a: Pamphlet on The Martin Anti-Friction Rocking Grates. Stockham Pipe & Fittings Company.
  - From Box 1 Folder 23: Miscellaneous-McBryde's Interests.
    - a: Fold out advertisement and review with photograph of Miss Amy Murray's lecture recitals of old Scottish songs and Ballads.
  - From Box 2 Folder 51: Harrison-Henderson.
    - a: Questionnaire from the United States Department of Agriculture office of Experiment Stations. Report of the Director of Farmers' Institutes.
    - b: Letter from a sister to McBryde.
  - From Box 2 Folder 60: Lilley-Lyon, 1901-1904.
    - a: Letter from J.H. Little Missionary, American S.S. Union concerning funding his son's education.
  - From Box 3 Folder 82: Soule-Stevens.
    - a: Grass Garden record for annual legumes, Blank form.
  - From Box 4 Folder 110: Mabee-Murrill, McBryde, 1905.
    - a: Newspaper articles advertising a detective who wishes to investigate the fires at V.P.I., piece titled " Some of the Most Important Criminal Cases Worked Successfully by the Maryland Detective Service that Have Appeared in the papers in the Past Two Years.
    - From Box 4 Folder 136: Albarez-Keeler, Campbell Incoming-Outgoing, 1906.
      - a: Memorandum concerning the sending of an Educational Commission to China, by Edmund J. James, President of the University of Illinois.
  - From Box 4 Folder 137: Larsen-Wood, Campbell Incoming-outgoing, 1906.
    - a: Letter to Campbell from parent.
  - From Box 4 Folder 144: Clothier-Cuthorell, 1906-1907.
    - a: Advertisement with pictures for Miss Nellie Amber Crossen Entertainer, Reader, Lecturer in Lecture- recitals, Popular Entertainments and Fictional Readings.
  - From Box 6 Folder 226: Bids & Contracts, 1900-1907.
    - a: Advertisement for Printing company and the use of Roman letters.